<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Benjamin Weare</title>
 <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="/"/>
 <updated>2025-04-16T23:07:47+01:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name>Benjamin Weare</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>TEM Hardware</title>
   <link href="/2025/04/16/Hardware/"/>
   <updated>2025-04-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>/2025/04/16/Hardware</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first time I met a transmission electron microscope (TEM) I was surprised at how tall it was, rising far over our heads. Behind it pumps, computers, and a forest of cables typing everything into a working instrument. I thought: “Why does it take up an entire room? What does all of it do?” I think a lot of people have a similar reaction, the sheer size of the machine demanding an explanation of it’s purpose and function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bright spark infusing life into a TEM is the electron source, without which the microscope would be so much scrap. Perching at the column’s peak, an electron gun emits and accelerates a beam of electrons. We often control the accelerating voltage, the kinetic energy of our electrons in kilo electron volts. Higher voltage gives faster electrons with smaller wavelength – a 200 keV electrons’ wavelength is 0.00251 nm, while visible light is hundreds of nanometres. For microscopy we want the beam monochromatic and bright, so
a small range of wavelengths and the beam emitted through a small angle range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the gun electrons are emitted into vacuum so we can apply acceleration. The simplest method is heating a material above it’s work function (at which point it will start spraying electrons out like a shaken-up drink can) the principle behind thermionic emission. Cheap thermionic sources are a bent tungsten wire, and expensive sources are lanthanum hexaboride crystals (LaB6); with cost similar to a cup of nice coffee or an old used car respectively. LaB6 crystals, which are a lovely purple colour, emit electrons from a smaller area and work at a lower temperature than tungsten hairpins, so they have better spatial coherency and are more monochromatic. Better than thermionic are Schottky sources, where a sharp oriented tungsten crystal has it’s work function lowered by a layer of semiconductor and the presence of an electric field to enhance thermionic emission, but we use a field-emission gun (or FEG) for the brightest and most monochromatic beams. Here a sharp tungsten crystal is placed into a strong electric field causing electrons to tunnel from the tip – no heating required. I find it interesting that FEGs have smaller beam current than thermionic sources but are brighter, as they emit through a smaller angle range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/hrdwr_img.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Left to right: a purple LaB6 crystal in a thermionic filament; the Gatan K3 camera at the nmRC; a copper mesh TEM grid; and a grid on a TEM holder.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a potter works raw clay emitted beams are shaped and guided in the column by electron lenses. They let us create magnified images and often dictate the resolution, the smallest distance we can usefully observe. Electromagnetic lenses look very different to their glass counterparts; a soft iron polepiece guides the magnetic field made by the coils of copper wire surrounding it. To stop resistive heating could affect the magnetic field lenes are actively cooled. Electrons travel through the bore of the polepiece steered by the magnetic field – the field is stronger away from the centre of the bore, allowing us to focus the beam to a point. The focal length of the lens (where electrons are focussed to a point) is controlled by field strength, which we can affect by changing the current in the copper coils. Some lenses have multiple polepieces to remove optical aberrations by changing the beam’s shape. To further shape the beam we can physically block it with apertures. They’re often a strip of metal (a diaphragm) with a series of four or five apertures of decreasing size machined into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the electrons pass through the sample they form an image of it, invisible to our eyes but not to our detectors. First is a phosphor viewing screen that glows green when illuminated with electrons; below that a digital camera, to convert the incoming electrons to a picture on a computer screen. Images are greyscale – darker areas mean less electron wave intensity, lighter areas more. Cameras might convert electrons into photons that are counted, such as complementary metal-oxide semiconductor (CMOS) detectors, while some of the newest cameras detect electrons directly. For spectroscopy, we have other detectors – the energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDS) detector is above the sample, picking up X-rays emitted from it when the beam passes through.
Samples are put onto TEM grids, of which there are different types. For routine work we often use an electron transparent film of carbon, some twenty nanometres thick, on top of a small copper mesh disc. We can see the disc to handle it (gently) with tweezers, even if we can’t see nanoscale pieces of matter we’ve deposited onto the carbon film. The grid attaches to the holder, a long metal rod which is easier to handle than a grid, which we insert through an airlock into the imaging chamber. 
Everything we’ve discussed so far happens under vacuum, as trying to emit from a high voltage source through atmosphere would destroy or damage the instrument. Even below atmospheric pressure too much gas in the column causes poor performance from contamination build-up. Hence the airlock to insert the sample, reducing the gas volume we have to pump out when we want to change samples. To get a good vacuum (around 10-5 Pa or better) we have a series of pumps working together; an ion pump’s exhaust may be handled by a diffusion pump, in turn handled by a rotary pump that exhausts to the atmosphere. The best vacuum is in the gun, while the detector chamber has a slightly worse vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the main elements making up the microscope; source, lenses, detectors, sample, and vacuum. For deeper understanding there are plenty of textbooks and old hands to consult, and getting your hands dirty operating the microscope will do wonders. Microscopy requires the impetus of your scientific curiosity to make the beam useful, without it the TEM is silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams DB, Carter CB. Transmission Electron Microscopy: A Textbook for Materials Science. 2nd ed. New York: Springer; 2008. Chapters 6-8. p. 67-129.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirkland AI, Chang SL-Y, Hutchinson JL. Atomic Resolution Transmission Electron Microscopy. In: Hawkes P, Spence J, editors. Springer Handbook of Microscopy. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2019. p. 3-48.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Nanoscale and Microscale Research Centre access to transmission electron microscopy equipment; and thanks to M Fay and I Cardillo-Zallo for input on technical content.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Introduction to TEM</title>
   <link href="/2025/04/06/Introduction-to-TEM/"/>
   <updated>2025-04-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>/2025/04/06/Introduction to TEM</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Microscopy lets us form beautiful images of tiny objects, magnified so we can see them clearly. There are references to using a glass of water to magnify letters as early as the first century CE, and the refinement of glass lenses in the sixteenth century and beyond allowed the discovery of biological cells via light microscopy. However, the size of what you can usefully look at with light is limited by the resolving power (or resolution) of a microscope, which is proportional to the wavelength of light used. If you use light with 400 nm wavelength, the lower limit of the visible light spectrum, your maximum resolution is around 150 nm. So, if two objects are closer together than 150 nm, they’ll blur together into one image when we look at them through our microscope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resolution limitation of light microscopes led to the invention of the transmission electron microscope in 1931 by Knoll and Ruska, and the related scanning transmission electron microscope was developed in the 1970s by the Crewe lab (who, according to one account, smoked cigars in the lab until it was realised this may be a source of airborne contamination). The maximum resolution of a modern TEM is less than a nanometre, due to the very short wavelength of fast electrons, and even greater resolution possible with high-resolution TEM. The development of the first transmission electron microscope earned half a Nobel Prize for Ruska in 1986; the field gained another Nobel Prize in 2017 for the development of cryo-TEM by to Dubochet, Frank, and Henderson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transmission electron microscopy may have a shorter history than light microscopy, but has cemented itself as a vital tool for looking at some of the smallest objects on Earth. TEM is important in materials science and in the life sciences, although it’s not often centre stage. An impressive recent example was using high-resolution TEM to image krypton atoms immobilised in fullerenes, where the individual krypton atoms can be seen in the TEM images (see below). TEM imaging was also important for the discovery and study of carbon nanotubes, nanometre-sized hollow cylinders of carbon which may have useful properties for advanced materials. Biological samples are often imaged at cryogenic temperatures. Images of SARS-CoV-2 were taken using electron microscopy, allowing studies of how the virus interacts with cells, and more broadly TEM allows very detailed histology and microbiology research to be performed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The operation of a TEM is analogous to the operation of a light microscope, but the details are very different – TEMs use electromagnetic lenses to steer the electrons through the column, and the inside of a TEM where the specimen is placed is kept under high vacuum. As well as being able to look at objects as small as an atom, the interaction between the electrons and the specimen tells us about the elemental composition of the specimen via energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDS) and electron energy loss spectroscopy (EELS), and we can investigate crystalline specimens using electron diffraction. This can all be done from the sample volume, meaning at it’s best TEM can be a holistic technique. Transmission electron microscopy is a powerful scientific tool with an interesting history. It is very relevant for a wide range of scientific questions but the sheer depth of the field can make TEM a little daunting to learn about, especially if you don’t have microscopy experience to give you a running start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth having a working knowledge of TEM if you intend to use the technique, and if you’re just curious about what we get up to in this corner of science then how TEMs work is fascinating. My aim for future TEM blogs is to discuss the fine details of the technique in plain language as an introduction. We will delve into the hardware that goes into a TEM, how to design experiments and prepare samples, as well as discuss the different kinds of information you can get from TEM. It should give you an idea of when you’d want to use TEM, and for which samples it is suitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally published as part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/beyond-microscope-welcome-world-tem-iqpce/?trackingId=6LFC5gNqlEn5VfkbsorISA%3D%3D&quot;&gt;Beyond the Microscope&lt;/a&gt; at the nmRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cardillo-Zallo I, et al. (2024). “Atomic-Scale Time-Resolved Imaging of Krypton Dimers, Chains and Transition to a One-Dimensional Gas”. ACS Nano. 18 (4): 2958-2971. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsnano.3c07853&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham L, Orenstein JM (2007). “Processing tissue and cells for transmission electron microscopy in diagnostic pathology and research”. Nature Protocols. 2 (10): 2439 – 2450. https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2007.304&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harris P (2018). “Transmission Electron Microscopy of Carbon: A Brief History”. C. 4 (1): 4. https://doi.org/10.3390/c4010004&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopfer H et al. (2020). “Hunting coronavirus by transmission electron microscopy – a guide to SARS-CoVo2-associated ultrastructural pathology in COVID-19 tissues”. Histopathology. 78 (3): 358-370. https://doi.org/10.1111/his.14264&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isaacson MS (2012). “Seeing Single Atoms”. Ultramicroscopy. 123: 3 – 12. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ultramic.2012.06.009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nobel Prize in Physics 1986 [Internet]. NobelPrize.org. Available from: https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/1986/ruska/lecture/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rochow TG, Tucker PA. “Introduction” in “Introduction to Microscopy by Means of Light, Electrons, X Rays, or Acoustics”. 2nd ed. New York (US): Plenum; 1994. p. 1 – 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams DB, Carter CB. “Transmission electron microscopy: a textbook for materials science”. 2nd ed. New York (US): Springer; 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
